Finding Aid for League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area Records 1932-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area Records 1932-1989
League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area.
Women's civic and voter education organization in Mt. Clemens, Michigan; includes administrative records, topical files and visual materials.
98119 Bm 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
3.5 linear feet
Mrs. Gerald W. Morris donated the collection in May 1998. Donor no. 8727
The collection is open for research.
The League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens was first organized in November 1927 as a study group to educate women about current voting issues and their civic responsibilities. In the following decades, the League expanded its mission to inform and influence political leaders, local governments, and the general voting public by means of political activism, sponsorship of speakers and debates, and fact-finding studies and publications. Although the League took positions on political issues, they did not support or oppose political candidates and parties. In 1972, the League became known as the League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area. In 1989, the League was disbanded due to declining active membership and lack of leadership.
The League's activities were determined at the national, state, and local levels. In later years, the state and national levels of the League of Women Voters had increasing influence on the activities, organization, and documentation of the Mount Clemens-Clinton Area League. Local League members met regularly at general and annual meetings and at morning, afternoon, or evening unit meetings. Board members and committee chairs also met separately at monthly board meetings. Board members included a president, two vice presidents, two secretaries, and a treasurer as well as various committee chairs. Examples of committees included voter's service, publications, finance, membership, national item, state item, local item, and nominations. New board members were elected in conjunction with annual meetings in March or April.
At unit meetings, the League discussed contemporary issues. In the late 1920s and 1930s, the League studied issues such as child labor and welfare, women in industry, tariff laws, political conditions in Germany and Japan, and public schools. In the 1940s, the League was interested in atomic energy, national defense programs, public health programs, inflation, unemployment, and the threat of Russia. In the 1950s, discussions centered around the United Nations, world trade, the federal loyalty security program, forms of municipal government, and local sales taxes. In the 1960s, the League focused on juvenile correction, water resources, public welfare, the peace-keeping role of the United Nations, China, and urban growth around Mount Clemens. In the 1970s, the League considered land use policies, environmental impact, energy resources, the financing of public education, and local urban development plans. In the 1980s, discussions were about toxic waste, transportation, health care, South Africa, national security, natural resources, vocational education, and the federal deficit.
The League was particularly active in the local community. Members researched local issues, campaigned for local reforms, distributed publications, and sponsored local activities. The League's first project was to study abuses of child labor in Mount Clemens. In the 1940s, the League demanded the establishment of a county health department, open elections with voting machines for school board members, and a better Child Labor Law in Michigan. In the 1950s, the League campaigned for a new city charter, permanent voter registration, a constitutional convention for Michigan, and a recreational center. The League also sponsored high school students to attend United Nations sessions. In the 1960s, the League organized an International Trade Fair and conducted surveys on Mount Clemens' school system and housing needs. It also studied water pollution in the Clinton River, supported the city development plan for urban renewal, and campaigned for the implementation of a city manager and commission form of local government. In the 1970s, the League actively opposed the channelization of the Clinton River and the construction of senior housing in MacArthur Park. It discovered local violations in the Housing and Urban Development guidelines, and it participated in studies on segregated schools in the Detroit area and regional governments in Southeast Michigan. In the 1980s, the League examined funding issues and the need for public libraries in outlying areas. Throughout its existence, the League created brochures with general information about the local community.
The Mount Clemens-Clinton Area League was probably best known for its non-partisan, didactic voter's service activities. League members distributed pamphlets that provided general information about elected officials and governmental organizations. Before elections, the League sponsored Voter's Guides in the local newspaper that gave factual information and candidates' positions on specific issues. To create the Voter's Guides, League members sent questionnaires to political candidates and asked them to respond succinctly to given questions. The League also organized candidate meetings before elections to acquaint voters with the candidates and current issues.
In summary, the papers of the League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area document the interests, activities, and dissolution of the League. The collection is significant for its coverage of politically charged issues in the Mount Clemens and Clinton Township area and for its documentation of the changing interests and participation of women in political processes.
The papers of the League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area document the activities and political positions of the League between 1932 and 1989. The collection is divided into three series: Administrative, Topical, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area.; League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens.; Mount Clemens (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Clinton (Macomb County, Mich.: Township)--Politics and government.; Women--Michigan--Mount Clemens--Societies and clubs.; Women--Michigan--Clinton (Macomb County, Mich.: Township)--Societies and clubs.; Municipal government--Michigan--Mount Clemens.; Environmental protection--Michigan--Mount Clemens.; Public Libraries--Michigan.; Recreation Centers--Michigan--Mount Clemens.; Schools--Michigan--Mount Clemens.
Subjects - Visual Material:
League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area.; League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens.; Exhibitions--Michigan--Mount Clemens.
Genre/Form:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series covers the period from 1932 to 1989 and is arranged alphabetically. The minutes provide the best continuous source of information about the activities and platforms of the League. The minutes of board meetings are nearly complete, but the unit and general meetings are better documented in earlier decades. The annual reports are valuable for documenting earlier decades of the League. From 1939 to 1958, board members and committee chairs submitted reports, but from 1961 to 1976, the annual reports were created on forms according to state and national guidelines. From 1964 to 1987, the annual meeting workbooks provide summary information about the year's activities and interests. The workbooks contain minutes from the annual meetings, budgets, treasury reports, reports from committee chairs, and current agendas and positions. Newsletters summarize issues raised in general, unit, and board meetings, provide interim project reports and reminders of activities, and address relationships among national, state, and local programs. The newsletters fill in documentary gaps between the annual reports and the annual meeting workbooks.
  - Annual Directories 1932-1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (scattered)
  - Annual Meeting Speeches 1986 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting Workbooks 1964-1987, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1939-1947, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1947-1948, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1983, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Budgets and Treasurer's Reports 1940-1989 (Box 1)
  - By-laws (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1944, 1953-1989, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Job Descriptions and Guidelines (Box 1)
  - Members' Skills and Interests Survey 1982 undated (Box 1)
  - Membership and Finance Report Forms 1975-1976, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists 1988-1989, undated (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - 1932-1954, 13 folders (Box 1)
    - 1954-1988, 33 folders (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - "League News," 1936, 1946-1950, 1953-1958, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Mount Clemens Voter"
      - 1959-1970, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - 1972-1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Bulletin," 1976-1986, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - "Voter," 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - "Bulletin," 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Policy (Box 2)
  - Reports from Delegates to National and State Conventions (Box 2)
- Topical
  The Topical series covers the period from 1958 to 1989 and is arranged alphabetically. It primarily contains the reports and information gathered for the League's multiple studies and surveys. It also includes materials from the Voter's Guide, such as the newspaper copies of the Voter's Guides and the questionnaires with biographical information and position statements from political candidates. League publications about Mount Clemens and Clinton Township are also represented.
  - Clinton River
    - Activities 1973-1980 (Box 3)
    - "Record of Opposition to the Corps of Army Engineers' Plan for Clinton River Channelization," 1970 (Box 3)
  - Election Law Study, Concurrence Statements 1977 (Box 3)
  - History (Box 3)
  - Improvements to M-59 (Box 3)
  - Intergovernmental Relations Study: Regional Organizations in Southeast Michigan 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Land Use 1980 undated (Box 3)
  - League of Women Voters Week and Other Tributes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Public Library Study, "Public Library Service for the Townships of Chesterfield, Clinton, Harrison, Macomb, and Ray," 1986 (Box 3)
  - Publications
    - "Appointment Calendar," 1962 (Box 3)
    - "Clinton Township," 1978 (Box 3)
    - "Know Mount Clemens," 1958 (Box 3)
    - "They Represent You!" 1951-1989 (Box 3)
  - Recreation Study for Mount Clemens 1961-1963 (Box 3)
  - "School Desegregation: Legal Precedents, Methods, Effects," 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - School System Survey in Mount Clemens 1967-1970 (Box 3)
  - Vocational Education (Box 3)
  - Voter's Guide
    - 1964-1988, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Interviews 1974-1984 (Box 3)
    - Questionnaires
      - 1982, 1984 undated (Box 3)
      - 1986 Primary, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1988 Primary, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1988 General Election (Box 3)
  - Voter's Service Activities 1979-1980, 1984 undated (Box 3)
  - Wetlands Campaign 1976-1979 (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series covers the period from 1935 to 1974 and primarily consists of newspaper clippings. Three of the scrapbooks are almost entirely newspaper clippings. The scrapbook about the International Trade Fair in 1962 contains photographs of the fair, advertisements, and correspondence. The color slides of the International Trade Fair primarily show various organizations' display booths and ceremonies.
  - Newspaper Clippings 1935-1983, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Color 35mm Slides from the International Trade Fair, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks
    - International Trade Fair 1962 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1941-1957 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1965-1969 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1973-1974 (Box 4)